Welcome to another episode of Five
Minute Physiology with Dr. Andy Galpin.
In the field of exercise science, we
describe muscle contractions in three
ways. Concentric, eccentric, and
isometric. Understanding the differences
between each of them and how to use it
in training will increase your results
while minimizing your likelihood of
injury. Concentric is the most popular.
It is the shortening of muscle while
generating force. Eccentric is the
opposite. Sometimes you've heard these
described as negatives. It's the
lengthening of muscle while generating
force and iso meaning same position
means you're generating force but not
moving at all. Really common examples of
concentric only movements would be
things like bicep curls or leg presses.
Eccentrics could be lat pull downs or
the lowering of the bench press to your
chest. While isometrics are any exercise
where you're holding the exact position,
say a wall squat, holding a bicep curl,
or anything else where you're not moving
but still contracting and working really
hard. Most multi- joint exercises use
all three. In the case of a bench press,
you actually would start with an
eccentric contraction as you're lowering
it to your chest. If you pause for a
quick second, that'd be isometric. And
then while you're coming back up, you
would hit the concentric phase. Some
exercises start concentric and end
eccentric and some do the exact
opposite. Almost all have isometric in
the middle. But think about the exercise
that you're doing and how you're
performing it because that will
determine which of these phases are
happening in which order. You can also
isolate them. So you can do isometric
only. Of course, you could do certain
exercises like say just lowering
yourself from a pull-up position,
resetting, jumping back up and going
back down again. And that would be
eccentric only. Or the exact opposite of
course could be doing the pull up all
the way up to the top, letting dropping
to the bottom and starting again. And
depending on what you're trying to get
with what exercise adaptation you're
working on, you might have more
advantages doing isometric only,
eccentric,
concentric, or a combination of them.
Eccentric exercises are great because
they allow you to produce more total
force. They're also really good for
learning and exercise because it
demonstrates and requires you to be
under more total control. They can also
be really then good for generating
muscle growth and hypertrophy. The
downside though is they're by definition
slower. Not always, but most of the time
that means you're lowering something on
your body and you can't go as fast as
possible when doing that. They also are
going to add more to your soreness. Now,
this doesn't necessarily mean that
they're breaking more muscles down.
Spoiler alert and maybe for another
video, that's not actually what happens.
But the reality of it is they are good
for muscle growth, strength, and overall
movement understanding. Concentric has
almost the exact opposite. It's great
for explosive stuff and power because
you can move really fast and you
generally you're pushing things away
from you. They can be good for learning
as well, but they won't produce as much
peak force and don't necessarily always
result in most maximal growth. To be
really clear, they're both doing all
that. What we're talking about is at the
end of the spectrum when you're giving
everything possible, which one has the
potential to the absolute most.
Isometrics are probably the most
misunderstood or underutilized. I
certainly know I didn't pay attention to
them for decades, which was a mistake. I
love them because you're able to focus
on certain positions. So whether you're
working around an injury or trying to
isolate an area of weakness, you can
lock in that and not have to worry about
moving through the entire range of
motion. They are fantastic for strength
and hypertrophy and especially good for
muscular endurance. The research on
isometric is really clear. They are
effective and in my opinion
underutilized. There are a ton of ways
you can integrate these into your
training program. You could separate
them by phases. For example, you could
spend two, four, or even six weeks doing
just eccentric work. Spend another
couple of weeks on just the isometric
and then another big chunk of time on
the concentric. That's a pretty common
setup, eccentric, isometric, and
concentric. Because think about it this
way, spend a bunch of time learning
control of the movement. Spend a bunch
of time making sure you own it in that
bottom or final position, and then a
bunch of time actually moving through
the concentric. That approach is
triphasic and is one way to integrate
all three. You could also do it in what
would be called an undulating weekly
program. So maybe Monday is eccentric,
Wednesday is isometric and Friday is
concentric. So we could do them across
multiple weeks where we focus on one at
a time or you can integrate them and do
the same individual week. You could also
do the exact same thing in a single
workout. You could start off the workout
eccentric, move to isometric, and then
move to concentric. Or really any
combination. So maybe you do one
eccentric exercise, you do five
isometrics and then one concentric or
any combination of them depending upon
how much focus and emphasis you want to
place on each individual one. going back
to the beginning which was what is our
goal? What's our outcome? What are we
working around? What are we working
with? And what are we needing for our
most optimal adaptation? Another
approach you could also take would be to
blend them within a set. So you could
say for example, you could do one or two
repetitions where you're focusing on the
eccentric, you're holding for a long
period of time and then finishing
concentric. So in that particular case,
you're expanding the time during
isometric. If you're still doing
eccentric and concentric in this single
individual repetition, but since you're
spending way more time holding that
position, you're going to get a more
much greater stimuli on the isometric
part. Or the opposite. Let's say you do
5 seconds or 8 seconds, 10 seconds
lowering, hold for one second and then
spend 1 second or 5 seconds or 10
seconds going back up. So hopefully this
helps you understand. You have tons of
options. Go all the way back to the
beginning. Think about what we're trying
to do, what emphasis you're trying to
place, and that will determine your
program design. I hope that made sense,
but it may be easier for you to just see
an example. Please keep in mind this is
just one random madeup scenario. It does
work, but there's plenty of options and
no reason to think this is the exact
right, perfect, or optimal setup by any
stretch of the imagination. Often times
when coaches are programming, they'll
give you three numbers next to your
workout. What they're representing there
is tempo. And that's specifically
telling you how much time to spend in
these different phases. So you could see
something on your chart that looks like
1 121 or 510 or something like that. In
this particular case, let's say you're
doing a plyometric exercise. You're
going to jump up and down, land, and
jump back up as high as you can, as fast
as you can. Well, in that particular
case, the eccentric is a zero. You're
going as fast as you can. The isometric
at the bottom is none because you're
actually trying to get back up in the
air as fast as you can. So that would be
0 0. And the concentric is also as fast
as possible. So we would probably not
even write a tempo there. And if we did,
it would be 00 0. Meaning go as fast in
all three phases as you possibly can. A
different example of that would be if
we're doing say a pause squat. Maybe
we're going to say go down in three,00
2003. Pause for two at the bottom and
then explode up as fast as you can. So
that might look like 320. So, we're
manipulating different phases based on
what we're trying to get. If we were to
blend these things into an individual
workout, it might look something like
this. The start of your workout, you're
doing your speed and power. That's going
to be a 0000 tempo, moving as fast as
you can, maybe some agility drills.
You're throwing stuff and you're
maximizing your peak power. Then you
might move into two or three exercises
geared more towards strength. Maybe
you're going to do a three second
eccentric because we want to make sure
we're under good control for whatever
we're doing. a one second pause. Same
idea, trying to stabilize, be safe, and
then we're going to explode up with a
concentric as fast as we can. We know
strength requires acceleration and so we
wouldn't want to intentionally go slow
if we're trying to maximize strength. So
maybe you do two or three exercises
focused on strength. You transition
there to maybe hypertrophy or muscular
endurance, and we do something the
opposite. We do a 3se secondond
eccentric, a 5-second hold, and then
whatever it takes you to lift the weight
back up. And you might only do two or
three repetitions because of the fatigue
associated with those extra long holds
at the beginning or the middle. You can
then finish at the end doing the exact
opposite actually where maybe you do a
two sec eentric, a two-cond hold, and a
5-second concentric. This is nice
because it makes the absolute load or
the weight really low, which should make
it easier on your joints, and you can
get a ton of fatigue, a ton of pump, and
feel really great in a way that doesn't
beat you up. Again, just a random
example to help you conceptualize how
this could look if you wanted to
integrate all three into a workout.
Infinite possibilities there. Explore
what works best for you and your
situation and goals. Before we leave
this, I want to throw one more quick
thing at you, and that is something
called eccentric overload. It's actually
been around a long time, but very few
people are aware of it, and almost
nobody uses it. My team has actually
published a paper on this very recently
and that is the idea of taking say 110
or 115 maybe even more percent of your
one rep max. It's only the eccentric
portion of it. You just say lower
yourself on the squat or the bench with
a really really really heavy load. Well,
spoiler alert, it's really effective at
a lot of things. I wouldn't try this if
you're a beginner or you don't know what
your one rep max is. A lot of caveats go
into something like that. It's an
advanced strategy, but very effective
and something that you should pay
attention to in the field. If you want
to hear more about that and see direct
examples, let me know, of course, the
comments section, and I'm happy to make
a video if that's something of interest.
Hopefully, this was enjoyable and it
helped you. Would love to hear how this
is working out. If any of you do make
any changes to your training, you try
anything based on this video, I would
love to hear how it went and get that
feedback. It's always a pleasure hearing
people tell me things worked or that
they were terrible. Whatever the case
may be, want to know about it. Thanks
again for checking out another episode
of FiveMinute Fizz and we'll see you
next time. If you enjoyed this and want
to keep learning more about human health
and performance, consider signing up for
the Catalyst. That's my completely free
newsletter where we share information
about places I've learned from, great
books, podcasts, social media, people to
follow, and other ways to stay upto-date
with the most recent evidenceinformed
approaches in this field. I'll put a
link to that newsletter in the
description below, as well as pinned to
the top comments, and I'll see you
there.